<Document>
# Surgery
Surgery is hands-on medical work: stitching up injuries and pulling out (or putting in) organs. You'll need a downed patient, a bedsheet, and the right surgical tools.

## Requirements
To begin surgery, you need:
- A [color=#a4885c]downed patient[/color] (you cannot operate on standing or conscious patients)
- A [color=#a4885c]bedsheet[/color] to drape the patient
- The correct [color=#a4885c]surgical tools[/color] for each step

You [color=#993333]cannot perform surgery on yourself[/color].

## Surgical Tools
<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="Scalpel"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="Retractor"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="Hemostat"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="Saw" Caption="bone saw"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="Cautery"/>
</Box>

## Starting Surgery
1. Make sure your patient is [color=#a4885c]downed[/color] (in crit, stunned, etc.)
2. Use a [color=#a4885c]bedsheet[/color] on the patient to open the procedure menu
3. Select a procedure from the radial menu
4. The patient is now draped and surgery begins

The bedsheet is only consumed when you confirm a procedure. Cancelling the menu wastes nothing.

## Surgery Surfaces
Buckle your patient to a surgery surface before starting, and the procedure goes faster:
<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OperatingTable" Caption="operating table (0.5x)"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="MedicalBed" Caption="medical bed (0.7x)"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="RollerBed" Caption="roller bed (0.8x)"/>
</Box>
Operating without a proper surface uses the default speed (1.0x).

## Performing Steps
Each procedure is a sequence of tool steps. Use the [color=#a4885c]correct tool[/color] on the draped patient to advance. Using the wrong tool gives a warning popup.

When all steps are done, use a [color=#a4885c]cautery[/color] on the patient to close the incision and finish the procedure. The cautery stops all bleeding and removes the drape.

## Procedures

### Tend Wounds (Brute)
Repairs physical damage (blunt, slash, piercing).
- [color=#a4885c]Scalpel[/color] - make incision
- [color=#a4885c]Retractor[/color] - retract skin
- [color=#a4885c]Hemostat[/color] - treat wounds (repeats automatically until healed)
- [color=#a4885c]Cautery[/color] - close incision

### Tend Wounds (Burn)
Treats burn damage (heat, shock, cold, caustic).
- [color=#a4885c]Scalpel[/color] - make incision
- [color=#a4885c]Retractor[/color] - retract skin
- [color=#a4885c]Hemostat[/color] - treat burns (repeats automatically until healed)
- [color=#a4885c]Cautery[/color] - close incision

### Organ Manipulation
Open the body cavity to remove or insert organs.
- [color=#a4885c]Scalpel[/color] - make incision
- [color=#a4885c]Retractor[/color] - retract skin
- [color=#a4885c]Hemostat[/color] - clamp vessels
- [color=#a4885c]Bone saw[/color] - saw through bone
- [color=#a4885c]Hemostat[/color] - select organ to remove (opens organ picker)
- [color=#a4885c]Cautery[/color] - close incision

To [color=#a4885c]insert[/color] an organ, hold it in your hand and use it on the draped patient during an active surgery.

## Cancelling Surgery
The patient can click the [color=#a4885c]drape alert[/color] on their HUD to remove the drape and cancel the procedure at any time.

## Tips
- Surgery causes some damage during the opening steps (incisions bleed, retractors bruise). Plan for this.
- The hemostat heals a fixed total per repeat, split across whatever damage types the patient actually has.
- Keep extra bedsheets handy. Each procedure uses one.
- Medbay's operating table is the fastest surface available.
</Document>
