<Document>
# Action bar

The slot row at the top of the screen. Each slot holds one action: a species ability, an item you're holding, combat mode, an emote, whatever's available. Click a slot or press its key to fire.

## Shape and look

[color=yellow]Settings > Misc > Action Bar[/color] controls the layout.

- [color=#a4885c]Rows[/color] and [color=#a4885c]Slots per row[/color] decide how many buttons are visible and how they wrap. Default is one row of ten.
- [color=#a4885c]Slot spacing[/color] is the gap between buttons.
- [color=#a4885c]Show keybind label[/color] toggles the small key letter in the corner of each slot.
- [color=#a4885c]Show empty slots (faint)[/color] draws the outline of unused slots so the shape is always visible.

Background opacity lives in [color=yellow]Settings > Accessibility[/color] with the other UI opacity sliders.

## Hotkeys

Defaults are [color=yellow][bold]1-0[/bold][/color] for the first row and [color=yellow][bold]Shift+1-0[/bold][/color] for the second. All 20 can be rebound two ways, and both write the same keybind:

1. [color=yellow]Settings > Controls[/color] has an [color=#a4885c]Assign action bar slot hotkeys[/color] checkbox at the top. Tick it, click any slot on the bar, press the key you want. The matching [color=#a4885c]Hotbar 1[/color], [color=#a4885c]Hotbar Shift 1[/color], etc. row updates.
2. Or scroll down that same options panel and click the key field next to the [color=#a4885c]Hotbar[/color] entry directly.

The slot's label updates immediately.

## Locking and auto-add

The actions window (open with [color=yellow][bold][keybind="OpenActionsMenu"][/bold][/color]) has two checkboxes worth knowing about.

- [color=#a4885c]Lock bar[/color] blocks right-click-clear and drag-to-rearrange. Clicking a slot to fire still works; the layout just can't be nudged by a misclick.
- [color=#a4885c]Auto-add new actions[/color]. When off, picking up an item or getting a new ability leaves the bar alone. The action still appears in the actions menu, it just doesn't push your curated slots around.

## Emotes

Every emote you'd see in the radial emote menu also appears as a draggable button in the actions menu. The filter dropdown there has an [color=#a4885c]Emote[/color] checkbox if you want to look at just those.

Drag one onto a hotbar slot. Rebind the slot's key if you want. Pressing that key plays the emote, same as typing the command.

Emote slot placement is saved.
</Document>
