<Document>
# Action bar

The slot row at the top of the screen. Each slot holds one action: a species ability, an item you're holding, combat mode, an emote, whatever's available. Click a slot or press its key to fire.

## Shape and look

[color=yellow]Settings > Misc > Action Bar[/color] controls the layout.

- [color=#a4885c]Rows[/color] and [color=#a4885c]Slots per row[/color] decide how many buttons are visible and how they wrap. Default is one row of ten.
- [color=#a4885c]Slot spacing[/color] is the gap between buttons.
- [color=#a4885c]Show keybind label[/color] toggles the small key letter in the corner of each slot.
- [color=#a4885c]Show empty slots (faint)[/color] draws the outline of unused slots so the shape is always visible.

Background opacity lives in [color=yellow]Settings > Accessibility[/color] with the other UI opacity sliders.

## Moving and locking the bar

The bar starts locked. Open the actions window ([color=yellow][bold][keybind="OpenActionsMenu"][/bold][/color]), click the [color=#a4885c]Presets[/color] button, and toggle [color=#a4885c]Lock bar[/color] to unlock it.

When unlocked, a small grab handle appears on the left edge of the bar. Drag it to reposition. While locked, drag-to-rearrange and right-click-clear are blocked so a misclick can't nudge a curated layout. Clicking a slot to fire still works either way.

## Hotkeys

Defaults are [color=yellow][bold]1-0[/bold][/color] for the first row and [color=yellow][bold]Shift+1-0[/bold][/color] for the second. All 20 can be rebound two ways, and both write the same keybind:

1. [color=yellow]Settings > Controls[/color] has an [color=#a4885c]Assign action bar slot hotkeys[/color] checkbox at the top. Tick it, click any slot on the bar, press the key you want. The matching [color=#a4885c]Hotbar 1[/color], [color=#a4885c]Hotbar Shift 1[/color], etc. row updates.
2. Or scroll down that same options panel and click the key field next to the [color=#a4885c]Hotbar[/color] entry directly.

The slot's label updates immediately.

## Auto-add new actions

The actions window has an [color=#a4885c]Auto-add new actions[/color] checkbox. When off, picking up an item or getting a new ability leaves the bar alone. The action still appears in the actions menu, it just doesn't push your curated slots around.

## Emotes

Every emote you'd see in the radial emote menu also appears as a draggable button in the actions menu. The filter dropdown there has an [color=#a4885c]Emote[/color] checkbox if you want to look at just those.

Drag one onto a hotbar slot. Rebind the slot's key if you want. Pressing that key plays the emote, same as typing the command.

## Presets

The actions window's [color=#a4885c]Presets[/color] button opens a panel for saving and reloading bar layouts. A preset is a snapshot of slot contents, bar size, position, and the lock toggle.

- Type a name into the [color=#a4885c]Save[/color] field and click the button to snapshot the current bar. Reusing a name overwrites the old preset.
- Each row has [color=#a4885c]Load[/color] and [color=#a4885c]Delete[/color] buttons. Load always re-locks the bar so a fresh layout can't be nudged before you've looked at it.
- [color=#a4885c]Reset[/color] repopulates the bar from your character's known actions (emotes excluded) and snaps the bar back to its default position. Size, spacing, labels, and lock state are left alone.

Presets are per-character. One saved as Bob the Engineer won't show up while you're playing Alice the Cargo Tech. The first preset matching your active character auto-loads on join, so a curated layout comes back without having to click Load each round.

Emote slot placements live inside the preset. If you drag an emote to a new slot mid-round and want it to stick, save a new preset.
</Document>
